<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog Posts | Dr. Emily Nordmann</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blog Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/me_2018</url>
      <title>Blog Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivot 1: Academic Serenity</title>
      <link>/post/pivot-1-academic-serenity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pivot-1-academic-serenity/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change, courage to change the things I can, and wisdom to know the difference - &lt;em&gt;Reinhold Niebuhr&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a nice list, calm your pants where you can, and always have wine in the fridge - &lt;em&gt;Emily Nordmann&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first in what I plan to be a weekly blog charting what I’ve been doing to redesign my courses for online/blended delivery. This isn’t going to be heavy on pedagogical arguments or citations, if you want that please see our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/qdh25/&#34;&gt;“10 Simple Rules for Supporting a Temporary online Pivot in Higher Education”&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, this is literally going to be a blog about what I’ve been doing - recording videos, updating assessment information, checking reading lists. I am a teaching-focused lecturer with experience of fully online delivery and whose research expertise is lecture capture and I still feel overwhelmed at the scale of the task in front of me so I figure that it might be helpful to others to read a concrete account of the nuts and bolts of what the pivot entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;my-courses&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you some context about the courses I’m working on, I am Year Lead for 1st year psychology at the University of Glasgow. Typically there’s about 500 students on the course, with just under half of them registered on a psychology programme and half who take it as an elective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the old normal, they would have three hour-long lectures a week and a two-hour practical lab once every two weeks, in which we did lots of small-group work focused on academic writing, in addition to teaching data skills and programming using R. The assessment was a final exam (with an essay and MCQ component), a coursework essay, and a lab portfolio of small-stakes MCQs, R worksheets, and a group presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;teamwork-makes-the-dreamwork&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teamwork makes the dreamwork&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my blog and I will be writing about my experience but I want to make it clear up front that none of this is done alone. I’m lucky to have a fantastic team to work with at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UofGPsychology&#34;&gt;UofG Psychology&lt;/a&gt; and everything we’re doing is a result of extensive and ongoing team discussions and consultations with lecturers, tutors, GTAs and students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;uncertainty&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most (all?) of us, I find the uncertainty about what life in September will look like and what will be possible (or sensible) difficult and stressful to process. It’s like when I think about the size of the universe and the scale of it all short-circuits my brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the answer we’ve given to incoming and prospective students about what teaching will be like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all universities, face-to-face teaching in 2020-2021 will depend on social distancing guidelines that the Scottish government has set in place. Our promise to you is that we will give you as much face-to-face contact and teaching as is possible. However, because we don’t yet know what specific guidelines will still be in place in September, it’s difficult to tell you right now exactly what will be possible. We know that this uncertainty is frustrating, believe us, we miss being in the classroom with our students so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the uncertainty we want to give you as much concrete information as we can given what we know now, rather than promise things we may not be able to deliver. Level 1 Psychology lectures involve a lot of people in a confined space, so at this point it is very unlikely that lectures can take place in person for the first semester. As the situation evolves, and depending on guidelines, this may be required for the second semester as well. Instead, our lectures will be pre-recorded to allow you flexibility, but there will also be a live watch party (think Netflix Party but with less Tiger King) at the regular lecture time so you can make contact directly with your lecturers and peers, ask questions, take part in interactive activities, and importantly to help establish a routine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is more difficult to give you an exact plan for labs and small-group teaching. Given that lab class sizes are smaller than lectures, for the second semester, we’re optimistic that we will be able to deliver them in person as normal. However, for the first semester the exact details of the social distancing guidelines mean we have to change how we teach labs temporarily. In both semesters you will receive labs led by a lecturer and one of our Graduate Teaching Assistants, one-to-one office hours and support, Peer-Assisted Learning (which are sessions run but students in other years to help you get support from students who have been through your course), and the opportunity to work with other students. You will learn all the content and skills and complete all the assessments that students in 2019-2020 did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our priority is giving you face-to-face contact to welcome you into the University community, and give you the student experience you deserve – making friends, talking to your lecturers, getting involved in community activities. We want to make sure you really feel like you are a part of Team UofG and so that is the type of contact we will prioritise. Depending on guidelines, we would really like to prioritise the use of campus space for things that make your university experience unique and special (like study groups, student societies, and getting to know staff and other students). How we do this will depend on the guidelines, but we want you to know what our priorities are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how to put that into action as course lead (and lecturer)? I’ve found it useful, and calming, to make a list of what I know and what I don’t know and structure the work I have to do in the summer around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things I know:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lectures will be delivered online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We cannot have a large in-person exam at the end of term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some assessment guidance will need updated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The organisation of the VLE needs to 100% super tight and clear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading and course materials need to be available online and accessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are going to use Teams to communicate with our students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t everything, but it’s a good chunk of concrete, actionable tasks and a positive starting point. I still don’t know how many students are actually going to turn up, if there’s going to be a second wave or local lockdowns I’ll need to deal with, or what the distancing guidelines are going to be come September. But that’s where the serenity, courage and wisdom come in (and let’s be real, not a small amount of wine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I started with the assessment focused tasks because it’s incredibly important that any changes are considered in light of the learning outcomes and that I think about what additional guidance they may need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The end-of-term exam will remain but rather than being in a drafty gym hall, the essay component will be a 24-hour open book exam and the MCQ component will be a Moodle quiz that’s also available for 24-hours but timed so that students have 60-minutes to complete it from when it’s first started. I have updated the assessment information to reflect this in addition to the ILOs and assessment guidance as the expectations of an open-book exam are slightly different (i.e., it can be more focused evaluation and argument than rote-memorising citations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously students completed 3 small-stakes MCQs (2% each) throughout the semester to encourage distributed practice. These remain in place but I have updated the assessment guidance and procedure to note that these quizzes will now be timed so that they can get used to the format before the bigger quiz for the end-of-term exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I started a conversation with our technicians and researchers about the best way to award credit for participating in online research. Previously this had been done manually by the researcher but now there will be much more research done online, we want to find a way to automate it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We set up a weekly catch-up with the Level 1 team. Not for any particular formal purpose but just to ensure that nothing comes as a surprise to anyone and that everyone has the opportunity to feedback on things as I work through the changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I transferred our Assessment Information Sheets to Sway rather than giving students pdfs. Sway is good for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quostar.com/blog/sway-for-office-365-overview/&#34;&gt;accessibility purposes&lt;/a&gt; and adapts the display for different devices whilst also allowing the reader to export a copy to pdf or Word if preferred. You can see an example of one of our assessment sheets &lt;a href=&#34;https://sway.office.com/RnxqSvogLgH0UEIn?ref=Link&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week I will continue with the assessments (the former group presentation is going to require a creative solution). I hope that this blog is helpful to some of you, or at the least, reassuring that even those of us who spend their time squawking on twitter like we know what we’re doing are really just trying to do things one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivot 1: Academic Serenity</title>
      <link>/post/pivot-1-known-unknowns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pivot-1-known-unknowns/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change, courage to change the things I can, and wisdom to know the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first in what I plan to be a weekly blog charting what I’ve been doing to redesign my courses for online/blended delivery. This isn’t going to be heavy on pedagogical arguments or citations, if you want that please see our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/qdh25/&#34;&gt;“10 Simple Rules for Supporting a Temporary online Pivot in Higher Education”&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, this is literally going to be a blog about what I’ve been doing - recording videos, updating assessment information, checking reading lists. I am a teaching-focused lecturer with experience of fully online delivery and whose research expertise is lecture capture and I still feel overwhelmed at the scale of the task in front of me so I figure that it might be helpful to others to read a concrete account of the nuts and bolts of what the pivot entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;my-courses&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you some context about the courses I’m working on, I am Year Lead for 1st year psychology at the University of Glasgow. Typically there’s about 500 students on the course, with just under half of them registered on a psychology programme and half who take it as an elective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the old normal, they would have three hour-long lectures a week and a two-hour practical lab once every two weeks, in which we did lots of small-group work focused on academic writing, in addition to teaching data skills and programming using R. The assessment was a final exam (with an essay and MCQ component), a coursework essay, and a lab portfolio of small-stakes MCQs, R worksheets, and a group presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;teamwork-makes-the-dreamwork&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teamwork makes the dreamwork&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my blog and I will be writing about my experience but I want to make it clear up front that none of this is done alone. I’m lucky to have a fantastic team to work with at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UofGPsychology&#34;&gt;UofG Psychology&lt;/a&gt; and everything we’re doing is a result of extensive and ongoing team discussions and consultations with lecturers, tutors, GTAs and students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;uncertainty&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most (all?) of us, I find the uncertainty about what life in September will look like and what will be possible (or sensible) to do incredibly difficult to process and extremely stressful. It’s like when I think about the size of the universe and the scale of it all short-circuits my brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the answer we’ve given to incoming and prospective students about what teaching will be like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all universities, face-to-face teaching in 2020-2021 will depend on social distancing guidelines that the Scottish government has set in place. Our promise to you is that we will give you as much face-to-face contact and teaching as is possible. However, because we don’t yet know what specific guidelines will still be in place in September, it’s difficult to tell you right now exactly what will be possible. We know that this uncertainty is frustrating, believe us, we miss being in the classroom with our students so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the uncertainty we want to give you as much concrete information as we can given what we know now, rather than promise things we may not be able to deliver. Level 1 Psychology lectures involve a lot of people in a confined space, so at this point it is very unlikely that lectures can take place in person for the first semester. As the situation evolves, and depending on guidelines, this may be required for the second semester as well. Instead, our lectures will be pre-recorded to allow you flexibility, but there will also be a live watch party (think Netflix Party but with less Tiger King) at the regular lecture time so you can make contact directly with your lecturers and peers, ask questions, take part in interactive activities, and importantly to help establish a routine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is more difficult to give you an exact plan for labs and small-group teaching. Given that lab class sizes are smaller than lectures, for the second semester, we’re optimistic that we will be able to deliver them in person as normal. However, for the first semester the exact details of the social distancing guidelines mean we have to change how we teach labs temporarily. In both semesters you will receive labs led by a lecturer and one of our Graduate Teaching Assistants, one-to-one office hours and support, Peer-Assisted Learning (which are sessions run but students in other years to help you get support from students who have been through your course), and the opportunity to work with other students. You will learn all the content and skills and complete all the assessments that students in 2019-2020 did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our priority is giving you face-to-face contact to welcome you into the University community, and give you the student experience you deserve – making friends, talking to your lecturers, getting involved in community activities. We want to make sure you really feel like you are a part of Team UofG and so that is the type of contact we will prioritise. Depending on guidelines, we would really like to prioritise the use of campus space for things that make your university experience unique and special (like study groups, student societies, and getting to know staff and other students). How we do this will depend on the guidelines, but we want you to know what our priorities are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how to put that into action as course lead (and lecturer)? I’ve found it useful, and calming, to make a list of what I know and what I don’t know and structure the work I have to do in the summer around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things I know:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lectures will be delivered online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We cannot have a large in-person exam at the end of term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some assessment guidance will need updated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The organisation of the VLE needs to 100% super tight and clear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading and course materials need to be available online and accessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are going to use Teams to communicate with our students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t everything, but it’s a good chunk of concrete, actionable tasks and a positive starting point. I’ve started with the assessment focused tasks because it’s incredibly important that any changes are considered in light of the learning outcomes and that I think about what additional guidance they may need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still don’t know how many students are actually going to turn up, if there’s going to be a second wave or local lockdowns I’ll need to deal with, or what the distancing guidelines are going to be come September. But that’s where the serenity, courage and wisdom come in (and let’s be real, not a small amount of wine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s what I’ve done this week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The end-of-term exam will remain but rather than being in a drafty gym hall, the essay component will be a 24-hour open book exam and the MCQ component will be a Moodle quiz that’s also available for 24-hours but timed so that students have 60-minutes to complete it from when it’s first started. I have updated the assessment information to reflect this in addition to the ILOs and assessment guidance as the expectations of an open-book exam are slightly different (i.e., it can be more focused evaluation and argument than rote-memorising citations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously students completed 3 small-stakes MCQs (2% each) throughout the semester to encourage distributed practice. These remain in place but I have updated the assessment guidance and procedure to note that these quizzes will now be timed so that they can get used to the format before the bigger quiz for the end-of-term exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started a conversation with our technicians and researchers about the best way to award credit for participating in online research. Previously this had been done manually by the researcher but now there will be much more research done online, we want to find a way to automate it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up a weekly catch-up with my Level 1 team. Not for any particular formal purpose but just to ensure that nothing comes as a surprise to anyone and that everyone has the opportunity to feedback on things as I work through the changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transferred our Assessment Information Sheets to Sway rather than giving students pdfs. Sway is good for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quostar.com/blog/sway-for-office-365-overview/&#34;&gt;accessibility purposes&lt;/a&gt; and adapts the display for different devices whilst also allowing the reader to export a copy to pdf or Word if preferred. You can see an example of one of our assessment sheets &lt;a href=&#34;https://sway.office.com/RnxqSvogLgH0UEIn?ref=Link&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week I will continue with the assessments (the former group presentation is going to require a creative solution). I hope that this blog is helpful to some of you, or at the least, reassuring that even those of us who spend their time squawking on twitter like we know what we’re doing are really just trying to do things one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture capture &amp; widening participation: keynote excerpt</title>
      <link>/post/lec-rec-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/lec-rec-keynote/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is an excerpt of a keynote speech I gave at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eduhub.ch/events/eduhub-days-2020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;eduhub days 2020&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started talking about lecture capture research, I was so concerned with showing academics that lecture capture wasn’t about to bring an end to academia as we know it that I put all of my focus on that link between attendance and recording use. Aside from the issues I’ve already talked about, I think that in doing so I neglected the most important point of lecture capture, its raison d&amp;rsquo;être, it’s humanity. Lecture capture, at it’s core, is a second chance &lt;em&gt;and that’s a good thing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some respects this isn’t too controversial; we know that non-native speakers and students with learning disabilities hugely appreciate the provision of recordings and we also know from the many studies on staff attitudes that these two issues are cited quite frequently as “acceptable” reasons to provide recordings, but lecture capture is more than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to how lecture recordings impact the experience of those with physical and mental health problems, we&amp;rsquo;ve got less evidence. It’s touched upon in a number of studies but I’m not aware of any work that has this as its main focus despite the fact that unavoidable absences that include illness are the number one reason students give for missing lectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that part of the reason there’s not been a great deal of work on this is because we, as learning tech advocates, have been cautious about making the case that lecture recordings could be used as a tool that would allow students to miss lectures. There’s that fear that if you bring up the subject of lecture capture and attendance in any capacity then the conversation will stall, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this isn’t to say that I believe that providing lecture capture reduces attendance, there’s more studies that show no effect than do and when they do it’s generally a small effect. This is simply to say that I’m now willing to recognise that some students have personal circumstances that mean they choose to watch a recording rather than attend and I don’t think this is something we should necessarily be trying to prevent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought a lot about why I’ve had this change in approach and I think that one reason is the job move I mentioned. I feel extremely lucky to be at the University of Glasgow for many reasons but one of them is the diversity, I mean, it’s still academia, it’s still the playground of the able-boded, white, middle-classes, but there’s been a definitive difference in the people who are in my classroom and the that people I work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those people is 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/eolasinntinn&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Steph Allan&lt;/a&gt; and I include her in this talk with her permission. Steph is a PhD student at the University of Glasgow, she’s in her 2nd year, she’s just had her first first-author publication accepted, she teaches on my 1st year course, and she recently came back from a trip to Palestine where she was teaching programming in R using open-source software and materials so that they could continue learning at no additional cost. She’s the type of person you want on your team and the type of person that academia needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steph also happens to have psychosis and she essentially didn’t go to any lectures for all of first year and she cites lecture recordings as the reason that she was able to continue her undergraduate degree and the reason she&amp;rsquo;s now doing a PhD. Not just because of the course content she could catch up on but all the other stuff that got captured, the enthusiasm of the lecturer, the class announcements, the insight into what academia actually involves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;While not a perfect substitution for being on campus, they captured elements such as a lecturer’s enthusiasm for a topic which was inspiring when trying to engage with the content away from campus. Furthermore, this meant I was privy to “class announcements” (For example, the psychology society hosting an event) which were not on the actual slides. I would not have gone to them, but at least I knew what was on. This helped demystify the hidden curriculum a bit as I could see academia was not just remembering facts and regurgitating them for exams, but also seemed to involve meeting up and discussing ideas…I would not be doing a PhD without lecture recordings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the counter-argument to this, I’ve heard it many times before, this is an exceptional case, if she wanted recordings she could have requested them through the disability service, this isn’t a reason to provide recordings for all and let me just put a pin in that for a moment and tell you about the second thing that’s happened to change my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I received funding from the Quality Assurance Agency in Scotland with my colleagues Jill MacKay from the University of Edinburgh and Jacqui Hutchinson from the University of Aberdeen to look at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enhancementthemes.ac.uk/current-enhancement-theme/student-engagement-and-demographics/widening-participation-with-lecture-recording#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;how lecture capture can be used to support widening participation&lt;/a&gt;. I think that widening participation might be a UK term so just in case, what this refers to is trying to make academia that little bit less of a white, middle-class haven. The standard definition of widening participation tends to focus on socio-economic variables, i.e., the aim is to try to encourage students from deprived areas into higher education but in recent years the definition is getting a bit broader to include people who have caring responsibilities and first generation students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had our first open meeting for this project back in December and the discussions we had there have really stuck with me. First, when we talk about lecture recordings being useful for certain groups of people, the conversation never normally goes much further than non-native speakers, learning disabilities, and health problems; but there’s a whole range of other, more hidden reasons why you might need a second chance at a lecture that are tied to widening participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our classrooms are becoming more diverse and that’s a good thing. But that diversity comes with a range of issues that aren’t hallmarks of the middle-class academic experience – poorer students are more likely to have caring responsibilities, they’re more likely to live at home and have a long and expensive commute, they’re more likely to need to work to support themselves, more likely to be the first person in their family to go to university which means they’re more likely to have poorer study skills when they first arrive because no-one at home could tell them what being in a lecture was going to be like. Lecture capture is a second chance for all of these people, it’s a second chance to participate fully in university life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand that whenever you put a system in place that some people will abuse it and take advantage of it. I understand that if we record our lectures then there will be a handful of students who don’t’ attend and out of no reason other than sheer laziness and apathy. But I also believe that you shouldn’t punish the most vulnerable because a few might not use the system as you intended. I grew up in poverty, I am one of the people that would now be categorised as a widening participation target, and I can assure you that whilst the pearly gates of academia might look pretty when you’re let in through the front door, there’s barbed wire on top if you have to try and climb over them to get in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge that there are good reasons not to record lectures, I would never want to stifle discussion or debate or change someone’s pedagogy to fit a recording and I am loud and clear that staff should  have the right to opt-out when recording would not be appropriate or if it would negatively impact on the educational experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I’m becoming increasingly angry about is a refusal to engage with the evidence, a refusal to listen to people who try and tell their stories of the impact that lecture recordings can have, a refusal from those who got the gates held open for them to look up and see the barbed wire because they just don’t want to record their lectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m angry that at our first meeting in December, Jill, Jacqui and I realised that we were all from a WP background and that maybe the reason there’s not been any research that looks at this is because no-one who hasn’t been through it themselves has cared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lecture capture isn’t a panacea by any means but there’s a socially progressive case to be made for it and it’s not an easy one to make because it involves admitting that recordings allow students to choose not to attend. What we need to do is highlight that many of those choices are for very good reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To return to the pin I put in the example of Steph and disability provision, I don’t agree with the argument that students should have to request access to lecture recordings through disability because aside from generalised benefits like helping to support note-taking it means you miss out on all of the people for whom what’s wrong with their life doesn’t come with a diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you could say that students could still ask for it if they wanted it and academics would probably agree but can you imagine how &lt;em&gt;humiliating&lt;/em&gt; that would be? “Dear Professor Smith, would it be ok if I record your lectures, you see, I’m the first person in my family to go to university and I’ve got no idea what I’m doing”. We have a responsibility to our students and I increasingly I think lecture recordings have become part of that responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
