<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog Posts | Dr. Emily Nordmann</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blog Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/me_2018</url>
      <title>Blog Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivot 5: Lights, Camera, Inaction</title>
      <link>/post/pivot-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pivot-5/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did this week was to rewrite a lecture on the history of psychology, not because of anything to do with the pivot, but rather following the recent Black Lives Matter protests I realised that I had significant room for improvement in the way I was presenting the history of our field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In pivot-related work, I started recording my lectures, or, I should say more accurately, I attempted to start recording my lectures. My first mistake was that I didn’t fully practice the lecture before I started recording. I have no idea why I did this. I always do a full run-through of every lecture I give, usually the night before, I can’t explain why I thought I didn’t need to do this when recording the lectures. I lecture from a script but I have always lectured from a script&lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; so that’s no excuse, maybe the lack of a live audience gave me a false sense of security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, it was a bit shite and I need to do it again. But, it was a good reminder to try and invoke as many of the cues I would normally have for a f2f lecture to give me the same performance level - for me this is doing a practice run-through, standing up, and putting on a shirt and tie and living my executive lesbian realness fantasy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also discovered a flaw in our plan to use Echo360’s Universal Capture to record the lectures. Whilst UC shows both the slides and your face if you’re streaming the video, you can only download either slides &amp;amp; audio OR face &amp;amp; audio. This is an issue because we think it’s really important for engagement particularly at level 1 that they can see our faces but also to reduce their data usage we want them to be able to download the lectures rather than needing to always be online (this also helps us with the watch parties in which we need to stream a video via Zoom and this will be better for bandwidth if it’s a local file). I think this is a real shame because the transcription editor for Echo is SO much better than anything else and it integrates with Moodle very well but, particularly for Level 1, engagement is the name of the game so we’re switching back to recording on Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing I’ve worked on this week though is setting up the lab activities and Moodle for both Level 1 and my MSc course for the first two weeks of the semester. I’ve worked through all of the slides, asynchronous activities, and Sway tutorials although I haven’t recorded anything yet which has nothing to do with Echo360 and everything to do with not mustering the drive to get dressed and do my make-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also started thinking about what kinds of social activities we can do. I don’t want it to be overkill (for both staff and students) so I thought perhaps something week 2, 6, and 10. Week 2 I’m thinking about doing a staff-student quiz for the entire school and in week 6 a Netflix party with a psychology-related film, again, with the entire school invited. I haven’t quite figured out what to do in week 10 aside from likely cry into my wine but hopefully something will occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to end on a positive reflection that came out of talking with my Director of Teaching &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Eavanmac&#34;&gt;Niamh Stack&lt;/a&gt;. Every year we get nervous. Every year the students are nervous. Every year something goes wrong - we stumble our words in a lecture, a video doesn’t play, there’s noisy building work next door. The mistakes will look different this year but we shouldn’t forget that they’re always there and that generally speaking, the students don’t care about them as long as they see that we’re trying our best. It’s going to be so easy to focus on what goes wrong this year, remember to be kind to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://notes.christellemozzati.fr/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/funny-guy-perfect-handsome-jerk-comic.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; Every time I admit that I lecture from a script someone likes to tell me that I shouldn’t and I will sound stilted and it will affect engagement. If you are considering giving me this advice let me save us both some time - I don’t sound stilted, my lectures are great, you do you and I’ll do me!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lec Rec impact</title>
      <link>/post/lec-rec-impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/lec-rec-impact/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;List of institutions linking to lecture capture guides from Nordmann et al. (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wordpress.aber.ac.uk/e-learning/2019/03/14/using-lecture-capture-effectively-tips-for-staff-and-students/&#34;&gt;University of Aberystwyth, UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cdn.auckland.ac.nz/assets/auckland/staff/learning-teaching/LectureCapture/Staff%20guide%20to%20lecture%20capture%20at%20UoA%20v2%2025.2.pdf&#34;&gt;University of Auckland, New Zealand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://canvas.bham.ac.uk/courses/21228/pages/panopto-lecture-capture&#34;&gt;University of Birmingham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cilt.uct.ac.za/sites/default/files/image_tool/images/83/LC%20Guide%20dark.pdf&#34;&gt;University of Cape Town South Africa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://help.uis.cam.ac.uk/service/teaching-and-learning/lc-oev/students/downloads/lcstudentguide/view&#34;&gt;University of Cambridge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sleguidance.atlassian.net/wiki/plugins/viewsource/viewpagesrc.action?pageId=115802123&#34;&gt;City University London, UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://celt.wp.derby.ac.uk/engaging-students-to-use-lecture-recordings-effectively-2/&#34;&gt;University of Derby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/files/atoms/files/using_lecture_recording.pdf&#34;&gt;University of Edinburgh, UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://howto.hyms.ac.uk/knowledge-base/using-lecture-recordings-a-guide-for-students/&#34;&gt;Hull York Medical School UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Glasgow (external link pending)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/students/success-guide/ug/effective-study/in-class-and-in-lectures/using-lecture-recordings/&#34;&gt;Imperial College London, UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://intranet.royalholloway.ac.uk/staff/teaching/e-learning/tools-services/lecture-recording-services-at-royal-holloway.aspx&#34;&gt;Royal Holloway, University of London, UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/lti/2018/01/23/impact-and-student-use-of-lecture-recording/&#34;&gt;London School of Economics, UK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.librarydevelopment.group.shef.ac.uk/understanding/using_lecture_recordings.pdf&#34;&gt;University of Sheffield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivot 4: Hitting the road</title>
      <link>/post/pivot-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pivot-4/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;It’s now clear that we’ll be running our small-group teaching remotely for the first semester in addition to the lectures (there will be additional f2f sessions, but core teaching will be online and I’ll talk about that in a later post). Broadly speaking the work they do in the labs in the first semester is either focused on academic writing (learning how to find and use evidence, scientific writing, researching their essay) and data skills (learning to wrangle and visualise data in R).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the old normal they would have a two-hour lab once every two weeks. In the new normal, they will have a 30-minute Zoom tutorial every week in addition to asynchronous activities. In the old normal, the labs would consist of some didactic content (the tutor presenting a pre-prepared presentation), individual and group activities, and live-coding of R. In the new normal, the didactic sections of the labs will be pre-recorded and made available asynchronously and the individual activities have also been converted. I am really loving &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.glowscotland.org.uk/as/ltttn/2017/09/22/how-to-use-sway-in-the-classroom/&#34;&gt;Microsoft Sway&lt;/a&gt; for this because I can combine everything into one lesson that contains the video, any written information, and embed Forms and other activities so everything is in the one place. The synchronous Zoom sessions will be devoted to group-work and the live-coding will be replaced by walkthrough videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, rather than just me recording the videos for the asynchronous lab content and walkthroughs, we’re going for a “team of credible experts” approach and you can expect the slogan t-shirts to be back from the printers any day now. In a nutshell, there are four lab tutors who also lecture and we’re going to divvy up the videos between us so that all students get to know all of us. We’re hoping that this will help create a sense of community - there’s enough of us to make it feel like a team, but not too many that we’re just yet another face they have to try and learn. Also from a pedagogical perspective, we think it will be nice for them to see how each of us has a slightly different approach to programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of last week I made a roadmap for both Level 1 and my MSc courses for the entire first semester. For each week I’ve mapped out the synchronous and asynchronous activities, assessment deadlines, and importantly, have given an estimate of how long I think each task will take students to complete so that I don’t accidentally overload them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing the roadmap I tried to keep the student’s weekly checklist in mind, and break their lab work down into admin tasks, academic writing tasks and data skills tasks. I’m not sure that the estimated timings are perfect, however, I want to model what successful time-management looks like as much as I can. I will take away these estimates in the second semester so that they progress in planning their own time, but I think this will help whilst they’re getting used to everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-08-07-pivot-4.en_files/progress%20tracker.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also took my own advice from our 10 Simple Rules paper and added a signposting section on Technology and Communication to Moodle. They’re likely going to have slightly different tech set-ups on each of their courses, so I want it to be clear what and how we’re going to communicate with them for psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-08-07-pivot-4.en_files/comms.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big thing this week was that I started properly working through my teaching materials this week. My original plan was to do everything on assessments, then the lectures, then the labs, however, I’ve decided that I’m going to do complete two week blocks of content (lectures &amp;amp; labs) and then switch to my other course and so on so that I can slowly start pushing back the point at which disaster might strike. My current aim is to have the first 5 weeks of term finished by the end of August at which point I will take a week of annual leave, and then when I come back I’ll try and work through the rest before teaching starts on the 21st. I don’t need to have everything done before teaching and I have told everyone on my course that they only need to have things done 2 weeks in advance, however, as course lead I want to give myself the space to firefight and react if possible. And if everything goes smoothly I’m not mad at the idea of being able to relax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For for level 1, I’ve got the slides and materials for the first two labs and the first lecture. Converting the labs to a) weekly and b) online has involved identifying which bits of the lab were didactic, individual, and group activities and determining what can be made asynchronous and what should be done live. For the Zoom tutorial, I’m conscious that everything tends to take longer online, so I have settled on a structure whereby 10-minutes of the tutorial will be devoted to Q&amp;amp;A and students will have a weekly form they can ask questions on to help facilitate this, and then one group activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For week 1, the Zoom tutorial is a getting-to-know-you style affair and making sure everyone knows how to use all the tech. I don’t want to put either the tutors or the students under the stress of trying to do a formal activity in the first week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-08-07-pivot-4.en_files/zoom.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also do some team bonding exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-08-07-pivot-4.en_files/zoom%202.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their asynchronous activities are a short video on types of evidence and they have several activities to work through, but there’s no reason that should be in the Zoom session. It works better asynchronously and I’d rather have the live sessions for community building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The activity for week 2 is also relatively light touch. They will be asked to do our reproducibility task individually, then we’ll put them into Breakout Rooms where they compare their efforts with their team and decide on a final version. This is actually a really important activity for them to understand why we teach them reproducible data skills but it’s also fun, gets them to do something with their team, and they have to share their images using e.g., Teams, so it’s a low-stakes way of ensuring that they really are ok with the technology. From week 3 once everyone is settled in, the activities will get more academic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-08-07-pivot-4.en_files/repro.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I redesigned my first lecture. The lecture was on How to Study, so the content needed slightly adjusted for online learning (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emilynordmann.com/project/how_to_study-_2020/&#34;&gt;you can see the slides here&lt;/a&gt;) but it also needed reformatted for the watch party approach we’re taking. Thankfully it was a short-ish lecture anyway so I didn’t need to cut anything to make it fit into 40 minutes (it’ll be about 30 mins didactic split across two videos) but I have converted a few activities I would do in the f2f lecture for the interactive bits. Normally I would ask them what learning style they think they are by putting their hands up (before telling them that learning styles are a myth), this time they will fill in a quick Microsoft Form at the start of the lecture about their beliefs about learning and studying and I will use the answers to this in the break as a discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that’s it. I flip-flop daily between feeling quite good about the amount of work I’ve done and then sheer terror at what’s still left to do, but actually getting started on slides etc. feels tangible and calming. In addition to the haircut I also got myself a ring light so next week I will do some recording and finish off week 2 of Level 1, and then switch to do the same for my Msc course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivot 3: Party</title>
      <link>/post/pivot-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pivot-3/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;This week I finished working through the assessment information for both my Level 1 course and my MSc Research Methods courses. The latter was fairly quick as that course was already delivered both online and offline and the assessments (R worksheets, pre-registration, quant report write-up) lend themselves easily to online assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing really of note for the interested pivot reader from this work was the update to the MCQ assessments for Level 1. Last year they were given three small-stakes MCQ assessments (each worth 2% of their grade) throughout the semester, to encourage them to study and keep up with the lecture content (as well as retrieval practice being good for learning). This year we’ve added in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peerwise.cs.auckland.ac.nz/&#34;&gt;PeerWise&lt;/a&gt;*, where they are also required to write one MCQ of their own. As I’m sure you’ve experienced, writing good MCQs is no easy task and to write challenging distractors requires you to understand the question you’ve set fully, so it’s a great learning activity and it also means they build up a huge bank of MCQs to revise from come exam time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to introduce this was nothing to do with the pivot, the School of Biology used it previously and it was extremely popular and requested by our class reps. The reason it’s in this blog is because if you’re looking for an activity to promote engagement through the semester, it’s a great choice. If you’d like more info, see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://sway.office.com/RnxqSvogLgH0UEIn?ref=Link&#34;&gt;assessment information&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sway.office.com/XWwc4wd1Hcm38jkc?ref=Link&#34;&gt;support&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I went to retrieve the link for PeerWise it was currently offline, here’s hoping it comes back!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;watch-party&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Watch party&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most calming thing I did this week was to do a test run of how we intend on running the lectures. Essentially, we’re going to try something akin to a Netflix Party. The lectures will be pre-recorded and chunked into ~15 minute videos, with a max of 40 minutes of didactic pre-recorded content. However, at the usual lecture time, we’re going to have a watch party whereby there will be a Zoom call and everyone will watch the chunks together. In-between the chunks, the lecturer will do interactive activities with the class - polls, discussion, Q&amp;amp;A. The type of interaction with depend on the size and the level of the class but hopefully you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rationale behind this approach was to try and balance staff and student workload and to balance what we know works for online with concerns about student engagement. The lectures are pre-recorded to allow for flexible asynchronous engagement, however, there’s also a synchronous event to promote engagement with the lecturer and to help students form a routine which I am particularly concerned about with new 1st years. The 15-minute chunks are better for online but the total run-time of 40 minutes is more realistic for workload than asking everyone to completely rewrite and restructure their lectures. Instead, the workload is channelled towards increasing engagement and active learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test run was really to test the tech and whether video sharing over Zoom would work. I tried several different methods, either streaming my video or playing a local copy and all of them worked fine. This is of course going to be hugely dependent on staff broadband speeds and bandwidth so I’ve come up with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gla-my.sharepoint.com/:w:/g/personal/emily_nordmann_glasgow_ac_uk/EXB_1AXHTfZNpBxmvg_lrjcBXbVQc2pFXKmWVDO5pS1coA?e=KWhQGr&#34;&gt;high and low bandwidth solutions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am 100% aware that this approach doesn’t work for everyone. Some students may not have the bandwidth (although we’re going to offer study space and access to tech to try and address this), some may not be able to make the synchronous session. That’s why the lectures are provided asynchronously as well, why the watch party will be recorded, why there’s also going to be a Teams channel where the lecturer will engage with the class. I don’t believe that perfect is possible (with anything but particularly with this) and I think we should focus on the fact that the old normal was incredibly far from inclusive and flexible and it’s huge progress for HE that inclusivity is being considered at scale for the first time. If anyone does have a solution that works for absolutely every student, I’ll buy it from you for 3 magic beans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;whats-in-a-name&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What’s in a name?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thing I did this week was to start to edit our &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyteachr.github.io/ug1-practical/&#34;&gt;data skills books&lt;/a&gt; for teaching R. The old Level 1 book was organised by Lab (Lab 1, Lab 2, Lab 3 etc.) and the sub-chapter headings were pre-class activities and in-class activities. In the old normal they had a 2 hour lab every two weeks, in the new normal, a lot of it will be asynchronous but they will have a 30-minute synchronous session every week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this means for my book is that I have had to rip it apart and put it back together again. I’ve removed any reference to pre-class and in-class and I’ve renamed the chapters to reflect the content (e.g., Loading data) rather than location they would be completed in. Why I didn’t do this originally I’m not sure. Importantly, the changes I’ve made have been modality neutral so that I don’t have to go back next year and change it again, e.g., “in this pre-class activity you will…” has become “in this chapter you will…” so it works regardless of how it is delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also need to do this for the MSc data skills book - at the moment there is a f2f and an ODL version but I will combine them into one modality-neutral copy. Again, why I didn’t do this before now is a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step with our data skills work is updating the instructions for how to access R. Previously students would have used the on-campus computers or installed on their laptops. To avoid any issues with installation and system requirements, we’re hopefully getting access to [RStudio Pro]&lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio-server-pro/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio-server-pro/&lt;/a&gt; which runs through a browser. This is a great move, although it does mean updating a lot of set-up instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also got a haircut, which means I can actually start recording, although I’m still a week or so from having anything to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivot 2: Academic, heal thyself</title>
      <link>/post/pivot-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pivot-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with starting your first blog with a pithy quote is that you feel pressured to do it for every one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I was going to have to start this blog by admitting that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t actually done much pivot work this week - I spent the first half of the week working on assessment stuff that has nothing to do with the change in delivery and is just part of the usual yearly updates and tweaks. And then I realised that it&amp;rsquo;s completely the wrong way to look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/qdh25&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10 Simple Rules*&lt;/a&gt; paper, we make the point (helpfully suggested by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/horrocks_simon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Simon Horrocks&lt;/a&gt;) that &lt;em&gt;For courses that already involve substantial use of the VLE and online content, it can be helpful to highlight that the pivot may be more accurately described as blended to online, rather than offline to online&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic, heal thyself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I updated the essay question and guidance** for the first year coursework essay and that&amp;rsquo;s just as much a part of the pivot as designing and recording asynchronous lab activities will be. This week was a good reminder that whilst a part of what I need to do is completely new and terrifying, the majority is the same work, or an adaptation of the same work I would usually do in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-presentation-but-make-it-covid&#34;&gt;Group presentation, but make it COVID&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the few assessments we have that needed more than minor tweaks was a group presentation that would normally be given in the final lab of the semester. The topic is &amp;ldquo;What three things would you tell yourself as a new level 1 student if you could hit rewind?&amp;rdquo; and students are asked to reflect on their first semester at university and what they would do differently. The entire thing has to be evidence-based and they draw on what they&amp;rsquo;ve learned about things like memory, learning, sleep, mental health, and study strategies from the lectures in addition to doing their own research. It&amp;rsquo;s a wonderful lab for many reasons - the presentations are funny, insightful, heart-warming, heart-breaking, and academically rigorous. Given that their first semester is going to be very different to what they expected from university life, we are very keen to retain the topic to give them a chance to reflect on all they have achieved and experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They will still work in groups and the topic will remain the same, but rather than a 10-minute presentation they will be given the choice between a 5-minute video, a blogpost, or a infographic poster. I stole this idea (and some of the learning outcomes and guidance) from my colleague Chiara Horlin&amp;rsquo;s Professional Skills course. This is a Level 3 science communication assessment so the scale and expectations are slightly different to my Level 1 adaptation but the core message here is to remember that there&amp;rsquo;s loads of good practice out there waiting to be appropriated. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know how to adapt your course or assessments, ask your colleagues, ask your educational development team, hell, ask on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this assessment I&amp;rsquo;ve given more guidance than I normally would, particularly when it comes to scaffolding the group-work because it is my firm belief that for 1st years this September, if it feels like spoon-feeding*** you&amp;rsquo;re probably doing it right. It&amp;rsquo;s still a bit of a work in-progress but the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sway.office.com/FGayGVQz6wAPxg3u?ref=Link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;assessment information is here&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;rsquo;d like to take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a technological perspective I&amp;rsquo;m hyper-aware that I have to provide suggestions for collaborative and creative tools that they can access freely. Their Office 365 package solves a lot of this - OneDrive, Word, PowerPoint and Sway cover a lot of bases but I&amp;rsquo;ve also tried to find alternatives, particularly for video recording and editing (Zoom, Animaker, InShot) and infographics (Canva).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;student-consultation&#34;&gt;Student consultation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I also hosted a consultation with teaching staff and GTAs where I invited 2019-2020 first year students to feedback on our plans for blended delivery for first year 2020-2021 given that they experienced the old-normal version of the course. Not too many turned up (to be fair to them, it&amp;rsquo;s July, they&amp;rsquo;re scattered all over the world, and their focus will be on what Level 2 will look like) but it was really useful to hear from those that did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were largely happy with our plans and were understanding of the constraints and uncertainty we&amp;rsquo;re working under, but the main thing I took away from the session is how important it was to be able to explain not only what we are planning, but why. It&amp;rsquo;s a level of detail regarding the underlying rationale and administration for teaching that we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily normally communicate**** but I think it was really helpful for them to understand the scope of everything we&amp;rsquo;ve had to consider when designing the course. We&amp;rsquo;ve recorded the session and I have sent it out in case those who couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it are interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My contact with incoming student is still relatively limited but we do have a Facebook group which will slowly fill up as more of them confirm their offers and finalise their decisions. They&amp;rsquo;ve already been provided with an information and FAQ pack but I&amp;rsquo;ve given them an anonymous form to ask any questions or write down anything they&amp;rsquo;re worried about with the view of doing a Q&amp;amp;A video in the next couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week I will continue working on assessment information and specifications. For level 1 I need to finish a few details and then move on to doing the same for my MSc conversion Research Methods course. If I have time, I&amp;rsquo;ll also start to write the mother of all week-by-week roadmaps for all of the learning activities for both lecture and labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* Yes, I am going to mention this paper in every blog because it&amp;rsquo;s great.&lt;br&gt;
** I think we&amp;rsquo;ve designed a great essay btw, you can check it out 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emilynordmann.com/project/missing_history/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
*** It is also my firm belief that what most of what is derogatively described as spoon-feeding is actually clearly signposted information that gives students the information they need to succeed without chance.&lt;br&gt;
**** We&amp;rsquo;re very open with our students and strongly believe in the power of co-creation, but room capacities and the definition of asynchronous and didactic teaching don&amp;rsquo;t often come up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pivot 1: Academic Serenity</title>
      <link>/post/pivot-1-academic-serenity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pivot-1-academic-serenity/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change, courage to change the things I can, and wisdom to know the difference - &lt;em&gt;Reinhold Niebuhr&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a nice list, calm your pants where you can, and always have wine in the fridge - &lt;em&gt;Emily Nordmann&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first in what I plan to be a weekly blog charting what I’ve been doing to redesign my courses for online/blended delivery. This isn’t going to be heavy on pedagogical arguments or citations, if you want that please see our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/qdh25/&#34;&gt;“10 Simple Rules for Supporting a Temporary online Pivot in Higher Education”&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, this is literally going to be a blog about what I’ve been doing - recording videos, updating assessment information, checking reading lists. I am a teaching-focused lecturer with experience of fully online delivery and whose research expertise is lecture capture and I still feel overwhelmed at the scale of the task in front of me so I figure that it might be helpful to others to read a concrete account of the nuts and bolts of what the pivot entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-course&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The course&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you some context, I am Year Lead for 1st year psychology at the University of Glasgow. Typically there’s about 500 students on the course, with just under half of them registered on a psychology programme and half who take it as an elective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the old normal, they would have three hour-long lectures a week delivered by a team of lecturers on various fields of psychology. In addition to the lectures, there was a two-hour practical lab once every two weeks in which the focus was on small-group work academic writing, data skills, and programming using R. The assessment was a final exam (with an essay and MCQ component), a coursework essay, and a lab portfolio of small-stakes MCQs, R worksheets, and a group presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;teamwork-makes-the-dreamwork&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teamwork makes the dreamwork&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my blog and I will be writing about my experience but I want to make it clear up front that none of this is done alone. I’m lucky to have a fantastic team to work with at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UofGPsychology&#34;&gt;UofG Psychology&lt;/a&gt; and everything we’re doing is a result of extensive and ongoing team discussions and consultations with lecturers, tutors, GTAs and students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;uncertainty&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most (all?) of us, I find the uncertainty about what life in September will look like and what will be possible (or sensible) difficult and stressful to process. It’s like when I think about the size of the universe and the scale of it all short-circuits my brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the answer we’ve given to incoming and prospective students about what teaching will be like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all universities, face-to-face teaching in 2020-2021 will depend on social distancing guidelines that the Scottish government has set in place. Our promise to you is that we will give you as much face-to-face contact and teaching as is possible. However, because we don’t yet know what specific guidelines will still be in place in September, it’s difficult to tell you right now exactly what will be possible. We know that this uncertainty is frustrating, believe us, we miss being in the classroom with our students so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the uncertainty we want to give you as much concrete information as we can given what we know now, rather than promise things we may not be able to deliver. Level 1 Psychology lectures involve a lot of people in a confined space, so at this point it is very unlikely that lectures can take place in person for the first semester. As the situation evolves, and depending on guidelines, this may be required for the second semester as well. Instead, our lectures will be pre-recorded to allow you flexibility, but there will also be a live watch party (think Netflix Party but with less Tiger King) at the regular lecture time so you can make contact directly with your lecturers and peers, ask questions, take part in interactive activities, and importantly to help establish a routine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is more difficult to give you an exact plan for labs and small-group teaching. Given that lab class sizes are smaller than lectures, for the second semester, we’re optimistic that we will be able to deliver them in person as normal. However, for the first semester the exact details of the social distancing guidelines mean we have to change how we teach labs temporarily. In both semesters you will receive labs led by a lecturer and one of our Graduate Teaching Assistants, one-to-one office hours and support, Peer-Assisted Learning (which are sessions run but students in other years to help you get support from students who have been through your course), and the opportunity to work with other students. You will learn all the content and skills and complete all the assessments that students in 2019-2020 did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our priority is giving you face-to-face contact to welcome you into the University community, and give you the student experience you deserve – making friends, talking to your lecturers, getting involved in community activities. We want to make sure you really feel like you are a part of Team UofG and so that is the type of contact we will prioritise. Depending on guidelines, we would really like to prioritise the use of campus space for things that make your university experience unique and special (like study groups, student societies, and getting to know staff and other students). How we do this will depend on the guidelines, but we want you to know what our priorities are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how to put that into action as course lead (and lecturer)? What do I do next? I’ve found it useful, and calming, to make a list of what I know and what I don’t know and structure the work I have to do in the summer around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things I know:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lectures will be delivered online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We cannot have a large in-person exam at the end of term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some assessment guidance will need updated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The organisation of the VLE needs to be 100% super tight and clear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading and course materials need to be available online and accessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are going to use Teams to communicate with our students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t everything, but it’s a good chunk of concrete, actionable tasks and a positive starting point. I still don’t know how many students are actually going to turn up, if there’s going to be a second wave or local lockdowns I’ll need to deal with, or what the distancing guidelines are going to be come September. But that’s where the serenity, courage and wisdom come in (and let’s be real, not a small amount of wine). We have a plan for how to deliver the labs remotely, blended, and fully face-to-face but that’s the bit that’s most affected by the uncertainty. So I’m just going to ignore it for a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I started with the assessment focused tasks because regardless of the exact type of blended delivery, it’s incredibly important that any changes are considered in light of the learning outcomes and that I think about what additional guidance they may need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end-of-term exam will remain but rather than being in a drafty gym hall, the essay component will be a 24-hour open book exam and the MCQ component will be a Moodle quiz that’s also available for 24-hours but timed so that students have 60-minutes to complete it from when it’s first started. I have updated the assessment information to reflect this in addition to the ILOs and assessment guidance as the expectations of an open-book exam are slightly different (i.e., it can be more focused on evaluation and argument than rote-memorising citations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously students completed 3 small-stakes MCQs (2% each) throughout the semester to encourage distributed practice. These remain in place but I have updated the assessment guidance and procedure to note that these quizzes will now be timed so that they can get used to the format before the bigger quiz for the end-of-term exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also started a conversation with our technicians and researchers about the best way to award credit for participating in online research. Previously this had been done manually by the researcher but now there will be much more research done online, we want to find a way to automate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I transferred our Assessment Information Sheets to Sway rather than giving students pdfs. Sway is good for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quostar.com/blog/sway-for-office-365-overview/&#34;&gt;accessibility purposes&lt;/a&gt; and adapts the display for different devices whilst also allowing the reader to export a copy to pdf or Word if preferred. You can see an example of one of our assessment sheets &lt;a href=&#34;https://sway.office.com/RnxqSvogLgH0UEIn?ref=Link&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we also set up a weekly catch-up with the Level 1 team. Not for any particular formal purpose but just to ensure that nothing comes as a surprise to anyone and that everyone has the opportunity to feedback on things as I work through the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week I will continue with working through the assessments (the group presentation is going to require a creative solution) before moving on to my lectures. I hope that this blog will be helpful to some of you, or at the very least, provide some reassurance that even those of us who spend our time squawking on twitter like we know what we’re doing are really just trying to do things one step at a time whilst the wine is chilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture capture &amp; widening participation: keynote excerpt</title>
      <link>/post/lec-rec-keynote/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/lec-rec-keynote/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is an excerpt of a keynote speech I gave at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eduhub.ch/events/eduhub-days-2020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;eduhub days 2020&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started talking about lecture capture research, I was so concerned with showing academics that lecture capture wasn’t about to bring an end to academia as we know it that I put all of my focus on that link between attendance and recording use. Aside from the issues I’ve already talked about, I think that in doing so I neglected the most important point of lecture capture, its raison d&amp;rsquo;être, it’s humanity. Lecture capture, at it’s core, is a second chance &lt;em&gt;and that’s a good thing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some respects this isn’t too controversial; we know that non-native speakers and students with learning disabilities hugely appreciate the provision of recordings and we also know from the many studies on staff attitudes that these two issues are cited quite frequently as “acceptable” reasons to provide recordings, but lecture capture is more than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to how lecture recordings impact the experience of those with physical and mental health problems, we&amp;rsquo;ve got less evidence. It’s touched upon in a number of studies but I’m not aware of any work that has this as its main focus despite the fact that unavoidable absences that include illness are the number one reason students give for missing lectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that part of the reason there’s not been a great deal of work on this is because we, as learning tech advocates, have been cautious about making the case that lecture recordings could be used as a tool that would allow students to miss lectures. There’s that fear that if you bring up the subject of lecture capture and attendance in any capacity then the conversation will stall, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this isn’t to say that I believe that providing lecture capture reduces attendance, there’s more studies that show no effect than do and when they do it’s generally a small effect. This is simply to say that I’m now willing to recognise that some students have personal circumstances that mean they choose to watch a recording rather than attend and I don’t think this is something we should necessarily be trying to prevent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought a lot about why I’ve had this change in approach and I think that one reason is the job move I mentioned. I feel extremely lucky to be at the University of Glasgow for many reasons but one of them is the diversity, I mean, it’s still academia, it’s still the playground of the able-boded, white, middle-classes, but there’s been a definitive difference in the people who are in my classroom and the that people I work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those people is 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/eolasinntinn&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Steph Allan&lt;/a&gt; and I include her in this talk with her permission. Steph is a PhD student at the University of Glasgow, she’s in her 2nd year, she’s just had her first first-author publication accepted, she teaches on my 1st year course, and she recently came back from a trip to Palestine where she was teaching programming in R using open-source software and materials so that they could continue learning at no additional cost. She’s the type of person you want on your team and the type of person that academia needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steph also happens to have psychosis and she essentially didn’t go to any lectures for all of first year and she cites lecture recordings as the reason that she was able to continue her undergraduate degree and the reason she&amp;rsquo;s now doing a PhD. Not just because of the course content she could catch up on but all the other stuff that got captured, the enthusiasm of the lecturer, the class announcements, the insight into what academia actually involves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;While not a perfect substitution for being on campus, they captured elements such as a lecturer’s enthusiasm for a topic which was inspiring when trying to engage with the content away from campus. Furthermore, this meant I was privy to “class announcements” (For example, the psychology society hosting an event) which were not on the actual slides. I would not have gone to them, but at least I knew what was on. This helped demystify the hidden curriculum a bit as I could see academia was not just remembering facts and regurgitating them for exams, but also seemed to involve meeting up and discussing ideas…I would not be doing a PhD without lecture recordings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the counter-argument to this, I’ve heard it many times before, this is an exceptional case, if she wanted recordings she could have requested them through the disability service, this isn’t a reason to provide recordings for all and let me just put a pin in that for a moment and tell you about the second thing that’s happened to change my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I received funding from the Quality Assurance Agency in Scotland with my colleagues Jill MacKay from the University of Edinburgh and Jacqui Hutchinson from the University of Aberdeen to look at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enhancementthemes.ac.uk/current-enhancement-theme/student-engagement-and-demographics/widening-participation-with-lecture-recording#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;how lecture capture can be used to support widening participation&lt;/a&gt;. I think that widening participation might be a UK term so just in case, what this refers to is trying to make academia that little bit less of a white, middle-class haven. The standard definition of widening participation tends to focus on socio-economic variables, i.e., the aim is to try to encourage students from deprived areas into higher education but in recent years the definition is getting a bit broader to include people who have caring responsibilities and first generation students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had our first open meeting for this project back in December and the discussions we had there have really stuck with me. First, when we talk about lecture recordings being useful for certain groups of people, the conversation never normally goes much further than non-native speakers, learning disabilities, and health problems; but there’s a whole range of other, more hidden reasons why you might need a second chance at a lecture that are tied to widening participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our classrooms are becoming more diverse and that’s a good thing. But that diversity comes with a range of issues that aren’t hallmarks of the middle-class academic experience – poorer students are more likely to have caring responsibilities, they’re more likely to live at home and have a long and expensive commute, they’re more likely to need to work to support themselves, more likely to be the first person in their family to go to university which means they’re more likely to have poorer study skills when they first arrive because no-one at home could tell them what being in a lecture was going to be like. Lecture capture is a second chance for all of these people, it’s a second chance to participate fully in university life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand that whenever you put a system in place that some people will abuse it and take advantage of it. I understand that if we record our lectures then there will be a handful of students who don’t’ attend and out of no reason other than sheer laziness and apathy. But I also believe that you shouldn’t punish the most vulnerable because a few might not use the system as you intended. I grew up in poverty, I am one of the people that would now be categorised as a widening participation target, and I can assure you that whilst the pearly gates of academia might look pretty when you’re let in through the front door, there’s barbed wire on top if you have to try and climb over them to get in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge that there are good reasons not to record lectures, I would never want to stifle discussion or debate or change someone’s pedagogy to fit a recording and I am loud and clear that staff should  have the right to opt-out when recording would not be appropriate or if it would negatively impact on the educational experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I’m becoming increasingly angry about is a refusal to engage with the evidence, a refusal to listen to people who try and tell their stories of the impact that lecture recordings can have, a refusal from those who got the gates held open for them to look up and see the barbed wire because they just don’t want to record their lectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m angry that at our first meeting in December, Jill, Jacqui and I realised that we were all from a WP background and that maybe the reason there’s not been any research that looks at this is because no-one who hasn’t been through it themselves has cared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lecture capture isn’t a panacea by any means but there’s a socially progressive case to be made for it and it’s not an easy one to make because it involves admitting that recordings allow students to choose not to attend. What we need to do is highlight that many of those choices are for very good reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To return to the pin I put in the example of Steph and disability provision, I don’t agree with the argument that students should have to request access to lecture recordings through disability because aside from generalised benefits like helping to support note-taking it means you miss out on all of the people for whom what’s wrong with their life doesn’t come with a diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you could say that students could still ask for it if they wanted it and academics would probably agree but can you imagine how &lt;em&gt;humiliating&lt;/em&gt; that would be? “Dear Professor Smith, would it be ok if I record your lectures, you see, I’m the first person in my family to go to university and I’ve got no idea what I’m doing”. We have a responsibility to our students and I increasingly I think lecture recordings have become part of that responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
