<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Study Strategies | Dr. Emily Nordmann</title>
    <link>/category/study-strategies/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/study-strategies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Study Strategies</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 16:32:32 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/me_2018</url>
      <title>Study Strategies</title>
      <link>/category/study-strategies/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Study 2022</title>
      <link>/project/2022-08-03-how-to-study-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 16:32:32 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/2022-08-03-how-to-study-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the 2022 update to my How to Study lecture. This introductory lecture is given to first year students in week 1 of term. The main focus of the lecture is on developing effective study strategies and to demystify some of the hidden curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topics covered include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to take notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What to do before, during, and after lectures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to use lecture recordings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to send an e-mail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which study strategies are effective and which are not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2022 updates partially involve returning to some pre-covid wording about in-person lectures and lecture recordings, but also takes account of how our practice has changed following the lessons learned from the pivot to online. In particular, for my lectures, I intend to keep the structure I developed for my 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.aldinhe.ac.uk/index.php/jldhe/article/view/696&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;watch parties&lt;/a&gt;, that is, I&amp;rsquo;m not returning to my original 50-minute lecture, I am keeping the chunks and the quizzes and the breaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/k2h9x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Download the slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are free to reuse, remix and adapt these slides without attribution, however, like any academic I occasionally need to prove my worth, so please let me know via e-mail or Twitter if you do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The purpose of Open Educational Resources is to reduce unnecessary financial burden on students and to help share good practice. I make as many of my teaching materials open access as I can for these reasons, however, if you have found them helpful and are in a position to do so, please consider making a donation to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bbstem.co.uk/donations/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Black British Professionals in STEM&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://prideinstem.org/shop/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pride in STEM&lt;/a&gt; (currently by buying a badge).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
